I'm waiting just another minute. I know that Scott Persson was
texting me with questions up to just a minute or two ago so I think he's got to be close by.
I didn't get to answer his questions because
I was busy trying to get signed on here but
I think he'll be joining us.
Okay, Scott, just disregard
the text I just sent you. I see you
popping in there.
And it's 701,
and I would like to call the public hearing to order.
And the first thing I'd like to do is we do have a couple of new folks joining us tonight.
I don't know who's on everybody else's screen, but Steve Nelson's got the prime spot on mine here. He's our newest member of the Planning and Zoning Commission
as of the July 1. So
he has taken over
a seat on the commission that was
vacated by Susan England who has gone off to be an alternate.
And we also have
Abby Winter
with us
tonight.
And
she is our
new
board clerk for the land use
department.
I'd like to thank
Mindy for all the great work that she's done over the last,
I don't know how long Mindy's
been with us,
but she's been here
for a little while now and has been
doing just an exceptional job.
I understand, I think she's living in South Windsor now, so the distance for if we went back to holding an in person meeting might be just a little excessive.
And
so she
resigned.
And we
got Abby
Winters
in place to
take her. That was a pretty remarkable quick turnaround. So
after we get done with the public hearing and all the official business of the night, I'll let Steve and Abby tell us a little bit about themselves.
And
I do see a phone number that joined us. Is that you with us, Leanne?
Yes.
>> Okay, very good. Thank you.
Okay, so we've called the public meeting to order. A couple of things
about that.
As you probably saw when you
signed in, the meeting is being recorded.
So
remember that when
you're making your comments.
One of the things that
I would like to
ask is that if members of the public are speaking
during the public hearing or for that matter during the
regular meeting that we get your first and last name.
I know when we are keeping the minutes
sometimes it's tough to
get those names and if we were to ever have to get back to you on anything,
it's nice to be able to have your full name so we can get ahold of you there.
As we do the public hearing and
I don't expect that it will go too long tonight because we primarily
I wanted to hold the hearing
open because Jim Allisley
was not able to attend the last meeting and wanted to give him a chance to speak on the record.
And so we'll give him that chance tonight. But during the public hearing, any of the commission members, including the alternates,
can
ask whatever questions you want. Once we get into deliberation at regular
meeting,
only those people who are actually seated,
and I think we've got the full
commission here tonight,
our aldermits will not be seated.
The aldenits won't be able to ask questions during the deliberation, only those people who will vote on
the application.
So that's
a little preliminary.
The purpose of the public hearing is let
me get rid of my diving alarm here.
The property known as 26 Old Farm Road aka Assessor's Map 28 Block 7 Lot Six-twenty
3,
applicants seeking a special permit for two rear lots in accordance with section 4.9
of the Andover zoning regulations
and a two lot open space cluster re subdivision in accordance with section 5.5
and Andover subdivision regulations in their entirety.
Note as proposed, this resubdivision
>> is comprised of one lot with access off Old Farms Road via an easement
and one lot accessed off Pine Ridge Drive near the cul de sac.
>> So with that,
I will give
the applicants
one last chance if there was anything else
that they wanted to discuss with your application before
we headed on. Now is your chance, George or Eric.
I don't have anything. Okay,
Eric?
>> Yeah, I mean, the only thing I would add is that there has,
Andrew Bushnell
has another
like revision to the plans that have just a few of the things that were brought up at the
first session of the public hearing.
Among them, the town of Coventry,
the appearances of the town of Coventry, and
a couple other things I can't quite recall off the top of my head, we have those.
Nothing material changed with
the plans that were discussed at
the last hearing.
The last part of this hearing. Yep,
>> Very good.
With that,
Agent Halsey, is there anything that you would like to
get into the public hearing with respect to
the application?
>> No, I've dealt with this
application and the applicants for quite some time. It was fairly
complicated application
involved wetlands.
And they've pretty much they've addressed
my concerns as they've gone. The only outstanding issue that I don't know is those that discussed is
the
drainage
structure that is situated
off the driveway.
And I'm
concerned that that be maintained in perpetuity.
Towards that end, I did throw a condition in the
draft motion that would address that.
That's where that came from.
Other than that, I've tried to
get all the information
from the applicant and their engineer.
I don't know if if
the
any some of the members of the Commission are
aware of the
wetlands.
Process
that that they went through. But part of it was
about some mitigation,
pulling some plants,
some invasive
species and planting
new plants over the course of time. And that is condition of the wetlands approval.
So it's not being addressed
by the Planning and Zoning Commission. That's all I have. Okay.
>> And with regards to that,
Jim, on
one of the questions,
and I don't know that I put that into the
conditions for approval that we were discussing earlier,
wanted to make sure that
we did not preclude
the applicants from removing
the invasive
plants
in the easement area. You know, it talks about not cutting
anything down and that sort of thing. We did ask them and they did agree that they were going to
remove the barbary
that's out there and
plant some native plants. So when we get to the point of
discussing
conditions of approval,
please keep me honest and make sure we get that part. Okay, think that can be addressed pretty easily. Yep,
very good.
Do any of the Commission members have any questions for the applicants at this point?
And Scott, you had asked me
if I had seen this one article of the regs and
I was not able to find that before we got online tonight.
So if there was a question or something
regarding that particular
section of the regs, I need some help understanding what that is. Okay.
I
don't know, I couldn't find it.
>> Okay. Thought,
yeah, I couldn't find it in there either. Now what made you come up with that particular number?
No, it's
when we get to
>> accessory apartments. Oh, okay. I got you. Yeah,
I'm sorry. Not this
application here.
I
will
take the opportunity to just ask the applicants one additional question for my
you helped me learn. This
was the application where I learned all about driveways.
But
you had a comment
in the notes that you considered
solar application
with respect to
your
development.
And I was wondering if you could elaborate on that. I think the regs actually ask
for what you considered
in that sort of thing. And I can go
I'll get that particular thing, but I'm just trying to make sure that I
think solar is the wave of the future and we should be encouraging
the ability to do that wherever we can.
>> I think then George jump in, feel free. The main thing we're considering this is the
orientation
of the structures.
Yep.
>> On one side of the
the on lot closer to Pine Ridge.
Most likely the, like, broadest face of the building is probably gonna be facing south, and we're we're thinking about that on the other side.
But we intend to,
we definitely intend to build with solar and,
you know, as feasible as it is, given the lot and the trees that are left behind where
we can make things face.
You know, there's tax credits and things you can qualify as you build
with them. We intend to take advantage of them. Okay.
>> Thank you. And just for everybody's information here, that article 7.15
of the subdivision rigs
says the plan submission for subdivision shall demonstrate to the commission that the applicant is considered in developing a plan using passive and active solar energy techniques
which would not significantly increase the cost of the housing to the buyer after tax credit subsidies
and exemptions. And so I think what we're really looking for there is the orientation of the house to take advantage of the sunlight.
And if you're doing that, that's all that we would ask for.
>> Yeah, that is our goal.
Eversource has programs that they have available.
Some of the programs have a time limit, but programs are always coming and going. And when we do actually start to build, we're going to take advantage of whatever programs are available from Eversource.
>> Okay.
I know know you Eric had mentioned that
you'd corrected some of the administrative items in the application.
One of the questions that came up last time
was
identification
on the drawings of
the
iron pins for boundary corners
and monumentation.
Those
were
not put on the drawings that we've had. So I guess my question is,
is the updated drawing been submitted yet
so that to Jim so that we have access to that or is that
still in the process of making it his way? And did you get those boundary
markings and monuments
required by the regulations
put in there?
>> Yeah,
the
drawing is
in transit. I think the plans are in transit. They probably have not arrived yet. I don't I don't think Andrew
sent them over.
So
you know we'll get them over shortly.
To answer the second part of the question.
We
did talk about this and I think there's on our side a little bit of uncertainty as to whether or not now,
like these need to be on the
plans at this moment.
One example
we discussed is, you know, we don't have approval of the subdivision,
you know line as of yet. Yeah. There's no survey pins there.
We're,
you know, so
is now the time that's required or is it is it something
we would do when we submit has built as a condition of the, like the CEO.
>> Agent Halsey, you got any insight on that? I share Eric's question as I was going through the regs. I know when we're all done, we get the as built drawings,
you know, expect to have it all done.
Let me believe that it would show proposed
an existing
monumentation.
So even though
the subdivision isn't approved yet, you could put a proposed
monument on the drawing
and then when it gets to be as built, would
take proposed off and they would all be existing at that point. Is that how that works, Agent Halsey?
That's fine. They could be on-site plant as proposed.
My preference is that they'd be labeled either existing or proposed.
>> Design professionals sometimes tend to leave that off and
you have to guess.
So that can be addressed as part of
the site plan, part of the as built. It shouldn't be a problem at all.
Okay.
>> Take a look at the draft motion and tweak it perhaps.
>> The as built is
when
the foundation is in, the surveyor comes and
picked up a corner of the
building and puts it on the print.
The
which
there's
quite a few on that lot,
should be on the print
it's brought to the commission.
>> They can be on the print as far as I'm concerned, they can be on the print as proposed.
And then
the as built would show that they are
installed,
that the pins are installed.
Usually done during typically
very done during the construction process.
>> And the reason for asking the question is, you know, when we get to items
like
change the notes to reflect the Andover instead of Coventry,
if that's already been accommodated,
we won't put that in a condition of approval just to get that list a little shorter.
But if the monumentation,
well now I think we're all a little clearer on how that should work.
It
would be nice
that when
the mylars get presented for my signature
after
the the
subdivision is approved that
it does have existing and proposed
monumentation
on there, and I would only call your attention to the fact that
there needs, there are, there is some monumentation
associated with the easements that you have that will clearly define that.
So we'll make sure we get that put right in the conditions.
I don't have any other questions for the applicants and at this time if there are any members of the public who are online,
Speak up and we'll
hear from you at this point. The fire department
>> letter, was that submitted?
I can't remember, Jim. Yes, it was. Okay, thank you.
>> Yeah, I'm just looking through who's
here and I don't see any members of the public and having heard none.
I would like looking
for somebody to make a motion that we close the public hearing.
So moved.
>> Thank you, Scott. Can I have a second on that?
Second it.
>> Okay.
With that,
all in favor of
closing the public hearing,
raise your hand so we can see.
Leanne, I can't see you raising your hand there.
I'll
have to get a voice vote from Leanne.
Aye. Okay, thanks Leanne.
Any opposed?
I didn't see it either. Okay.
>> I see
no opposition.
So the
motion passes
five-zero-zero. And
at this point,
I would like to call
the regular meeting to order at 07:21.
Roll call and seating of alternates.
I see
regular members Anne Cremay,
Scott Persson,
Steve Nelson,
Leigh Ann Hutchinson, and myself
all present,
in addition to Anne Blanchard
and Kevin
Arneson
present.
So neither alternates will be seated. Susan England is absent tonight as an alternate.
Item three on the agenda is additions or changes to the agenda. Anybody have any additions or changes?
Hearing none, we'll move on to item four,
public comment.
Anybody from the public that's
present that wants to talk on
any item other than the
subdivision we just had the public hearing on?
Hearing none, I'll move down to old business item 5A
and it's the application of George Korea and Eric and Melissa Liteska,
28 Old Farms Road,
aka Assessor's Map 28 Block 7, Lot Six-twenty
3.
Applicant is seeking a special permit for one rear lot, two in total, and two open
space cluster subdivisions in accordance with Section five of the Andover subdivision regulations in their entirety.
At this point, Agent Halsey, do you have any other comments
on
the application?
>> No, just for clarity.
There was
a rear lot approved years ago.
So at this point, they're looking for one additional. So at one point,
says
one lot and the other it says two, just a total of two, one additional.
Just for clarification. Yep. Thank you. Okay.
>> Very good.
Would anybody like to make a motion to approve the subdivision?
And when we get into the discussion on any motion that we have, we would go through conditions of approval as part of that discussion.
>> Commissioner Larson, I do have the draft motion,
which you're welcome to use. Can
you call that up on our screen?
>> I can't. I'm on my iPad.
I can read it to you.
>> No,
I think Mindy has got it there for us.
Yep, so stop Yep. Right there. We'll give us a chance to all
read through that.
>> I do want to point out that there were no waivers requested.
There are no there's no need to act on waivers.
It's easy to overlook.
>> Scroll down a little bit there, Mindy.
Thank you.
Okay, the thing that that I don't see in the proposal
in
we can add is in
the
easement,
we should authorize removal
of invasive
plants.
So Mindy, if you can scroll back up to where it talked about the easement in here. Think that was.
Covered
it. Where
is that covered? Number two.
>> However,
I
am not sure that I ever addressed the monumentation
of
of that
of the of the open space area.
Okay.
>> I'm trying to I mean, the applicant submitted
a draft.
Yep.
I
wasn't going to have it reviewed before
it was approved just
because anyone incurred the legal expense, quite frankly.
And the form
they use has been used before it was used to came
from Grimaldi's.
So
the format has been
is not new to to our land use council.
I'm
not sure where it originally came from, but he is he approved Grimaldi's
and this one.
The
Korea
Tesco,
the covenant was based on that.
>> Okay.
And
just for the applicant's information
here, when
there are couple of comments on the driveway.
Did
we
get a letter from Brandon,
Jim, saying
that he thought the driveway supported to 70,000 pounds or
>> addressed it by under here that he just said add notes that the driveway shall be capable of supporting emergency equipment up to 70,000 pounds
design construction materials, be certified by a professional engineer.
That should be professional, not profession. I mis
engineer and submit it to the town for you prior to construction.
So by adding that note, it's required it's requiring
that that be addressed at the time of construction. Okay.
That's the way he addressed it in his
comments.
>> Now, just remember seeing
some
letter that we got that you sent out late this afternoon
from Brandon, and I can't remember.
No, that was about the gravel pit. Okay, so that's a different and that was not posted.
>> So I'll
bring that up under the gravel pit
when we get there.
>> So
where can we add what you were talking about, Jed?
Invasive.
>> I'll
get there in a minute. I was just looking to make sure I've got a note, I will read it off here in a minute. And I was trying to see if the
draft motion here had
monumentation
in it.
>> It does, but I want to be clear what
monumentation is for the open space I think, right? Well it talks about monumentation.
Let me
>> go down to I think it's
on two there down.
>> So under Monumentation
Section
7.12
of our subdivision regs.
It says iron pin shall be installed at all lot corners. The commission shall require installation of such monuments
in iron pins as a condition of approval of the subdivision or re subdivision.
Doesn't mean they need to be installed already.
It's just a requirement
that they are installed.
>> Right,
but this is this is saying monument monumentation
that
our regulation
said
all monumentation
and steel pins.
So these are two different things. Steel pins and monumentation are two different things. Yep, I understand. And there's some words in there that talk about
>> monuments shall be placed at all block corners, angle points, points of curves in streets and at intermediate points
on tangents over 600 feet in length in principle corners of the lots.
>> All I'm getting at Jed is that it says the monumentation.
It doesn't say monumentation
and impingement.
>> Point taken. I honestly use the term interchangeably but perhaps wrong.
>> And I know in here, and I can't put my finger on it right at the moment,
it does talk about
under the conservation easement that
monuments
be installed there to identify the
easement.
>> And I just tried to address that by way of number four there. Yeah,
okay.
>> So you just need to change that number three to all monumentation
and pins will be installed.
>> Okay. And I'm looking back
for which
number was it where we're changing profession
to professional or whatever that was that you had a comment, Jim? Well, it's under one. It's the £170,000,
right underneath 70,000 pounds. Yeah, yeah, third note. Just
>> change profession to professional.
If you go to number six,
just want to make sure that it's clear what I'm trying to do here is
the applicant shall take appropriate action to ensure that the drainage structure shown on the approved plan is maintained in perpetuity.
What I'm talking about here is there is a drainage structure
that's on the plan.
It's
designed to accommodate
the driveway drainage, the driveway leading
from Old Farms Road.
I'm not sure the best way,
I mean, basically
that can't be built. You couldn't put
a building on that space in that structure area, for instance.
So I'm looking for some sort of language in the land records. I'm not sure what is the best approach. So I'm kind of deferring. It's really a legal
issue. And I was just throwing it back to the applicant
and the applicant's attorney
could handle it by way of a deed, in the deed. I don't know. I'm leaving it open
for them.
That's
what I'm getting
at by way of number six.
>> Okay, so at this point I
had the following
additions or changes
to what's displayed on the screen.
On
condition one, the third note,
we would change profession to professional.
Under item three,
we would add after monuments
and iron pins.
And in item four,
we would add
removal of invasive plants from the easement
is authorized.
>> From the from the area,
from the open space area.
The open space easement
>> from the area.
Easement to me sounds like the document.
Maybe it's just me.
>> Okay, so number
four would be removal of invasive plants
from the open space area is authorized.
>> Sure.
And that'll be addressed when when the covenant is reviewed.
And the covenant should should have that language in it.
Yeah. In my opinion.
If that's what you want, that's where it belongs.
>> Okay, and I was looking
and you thought maybe it might not be necessary,
but I thought we were going to have
an item
on
damage
to
the Dubies driveway
as a result of
equipment
or materials being brought into the
building site would be repaired by the applicants.
I think that's in there.
Number
five.
Okay, very good. Yep. So that's there. Okay.
>> Just
just to be clear,
I'm referencing
the plan that you all reviewed, the plan that is on
the website, the plan that I have a paper copy of.
And as far as I'm concerned, the plan that Andrew changed,
that's that's a worksheet for him.
You know, I'd like to see him incorporate
whatever changes
the Commission
adds as condition.
Commissioner Andrew But I don't want to get
I don't want to confuse things with another plan that that was never presented
so I'm referencing the plan that
we revised.
Commissioner Andrew I believe it's I have a date on there of I believe 08/2020
and revised through 06/1421
I believe.
I agree. And
>> that's why I didn't make an issue of removing the Andover to Coventry
or vice versa there.
>> Okay. And that should be all in here. I believe it is.
I want it clear that this
draft motion is intended to work with in concert with
the plan revised to 06/14
and not any subsequent plan.
Okay.
And that's what it says.
Yes.
>> Okay.
So at this point I am looking for a motion to approve the application with the conditions
as specified.
>> That. Second, this is Leanne. Oh, I'm sorry, Scott. I
guess you weren't done. No. Go ahead, Leanne.
>> No. I was just gonna second it, but I wasn't sure.
I don't know if I cut you up as to how much of it you were gonna repeat.
No.
I move to approve the plan as specified.
Then I'll second.
Any discussion?
>> I want further comment. I hope I structured
this correctly. I mean, the applicant needs a needs a special permit in order to get the subdivision approved.
I put them together. Hope that's
I assume that's okay.
I could have structured it separately so that special permit was approved first.
And then the subdivision was acted upon.
I didn't.
I think this is okay.
>> Okay,
Jim,
on the
on what we have displayed right now.
Yes. Under item one,
it's the precast concrete box culvert
blah blah blah.
Does that line end with page six or is page six in there an artifact
of it going over from one page to the next in something we were working?
I see page six on there between that and the driveways on that exceed a grade of 10%.
>> I believe those two
comments
below that are page six,
are on page six of the plans.
Okay,
you're right.
>> That is, okay. Yeah, I could have made that clearer, suppose.
>> Nope, just so we all understand
what that is. Okay,
Any other discussion on the motion?
Hearing no further discussion,
I will call for a roll call vote.
Anne Gremay?
Aye.
Scott Peterson?
Leigh Ann Hutchinson?
Aye.
Steve Nelson?
>> And I vote aye as well.
Motion carries five-zero-zero.
Congratulations
to Eric and George. It's been a long journey.
And we took another big step forward tonight.
Thank you very much, everyone. Thank you. Thank
you, guys.
>> So again,
the approval will be run-in
the newspaper.
I think we'll try and get that in next week and there's a two week
period after that that we can wait for an appeal before we actually start doing anything. But I think it'll probably be two weeks at this point before you get going there.
So
I'm hoping that not delay you any more than we need to.
Thank you.
That wraps up that.
The
next
item on the old business is
discussion,
possible action, planning and zoning application
20 One-four,
128 Wheeling Road.
Applicant is seeking a site plan approval for accessory apartment in accordance with section 4.11
of the Andover zoning regulations.
And I think the applicant is with us tonight. I saw him.
I am present.
>> Okay, Adam. The
as
you recall,
the
item I struggled with
last time was
regulations.
Send us to,
know, the first
thing in there is just talking about
requirements of Section 11.2
space requirements are satisfied.
And
as I go to Section 11.2,
it talks about
the minimum lot size of 60,000
square feet.
And
if I'm not mistaken, your lot
is short of
that amount.
Is
that correct?
Yeah, you spoke last time, that is correct. Yeah,
your lot is about 50,000.
50,000, correct.
>> I guess I tried to look at this
from the perspective of,
is it an administrative
oversight
in that when we changed
Andover lot size used to be 40,000
square feet and 80,000 square feet. When we went to
the Andover rural
development,
we made the lot requirements 60,000
square feet.
Did we not
catch all the little
pieces of that and have an unintended
consequence where we made the lot
smaller
than our regulation?
We precluded
a normal sized lot in the past from being able to put on the accessory apartment.
Certainly that
would be an item for the Commission to
determine
and vote on.
I think
however
the requirement got in there,
again,
for the Planning and Zoning Commission, we can make
almost whatever rules we want.
But once the rules are the rules, whether we like them or not, is no longer applicable, we have to abide by them. And
so
my thought is that as of today,
you don't meet the size requirement.
And there's probably
two options
there.
One we talked last
meeting
about the potential to go to
the zoning board of appeals
and
I can't
say how that would go there to present
why you've got a hardship
there. I can tell you when we did last modify the
accessory apartment regulations,
we were concerned about small lots
and putting accessory apartments on them. And
that's why in the Lake Regs we specify
the minimum lot size in the Lake District with all the small lots there
is 120,000
square feet.
Other thing that
comes into play, and I don't know what your time frame for
needing
to
do the accessory apartment is,
But the state of Connecticut
recently passed a lot of legislative
changes
and I don't understand
all of those changes yet,
but there are some significant changes
with respect to accessory apartments. Apartments.
And I think it's going to make accessory apartments
easier to put in,
almost
where it could be a matter of right where you don't need to go to Planning and Zoning Commission.
Planning and Zoning Commission has an opportunity to opt out of that,
but we haven't discussed at all
what
the thoughts of the different members are on
that and I don't
want to do that tonight.
We'll be doing that
in the not too distant future as we go through the creation
of an affordable housing plan for Andover
where accessory apartments are a big part of
that plan.
So anyhow,
for tonight
we can choose to,
you can choose to withdraw your application at this point
or
we can vote on
the application.
And my suspicion is it might not pass because of that,
but we owe you that for putting in
an application.
And so I'm looking for
your thoughts on how you would like the Commission to Okay,
>> I I don't want to withdraw it.
If we choose to vote on it and it doesn't pass, can I take it to Zoning Board of Appeals or does it just completely get shut down? I guess is my question.
>> Jim, correct me if I'm wrong, but if it does not get approved here, you can take it to the zoning board of appeals.
>> So that's not Actually, is nothing in the legislation
that precludes you from another special permit application
immediately. There is language to that effect for a variance. A variance does not have to The ZBA does not have to listen to a variance or
entertain a variance
that's not substantially different for six months.
No such regulation
in the planning and zoning in the planning regulation in the zoning regulations.
Can I just touch just mention,
you know, I did look at the regulate at the minutes
for when the changes to the when the ARD was established
and also when the accessory apartment regulation was changed? Well, no, it was changed
just for detached.
And there was
no discussion.
I saw nothing in the minutes
that led me to believe that anybody thought about it. I did not initially bring it to the applicant's attention because I didn't think of it.
Part of the reason is if somebody comes in for
a building permit, for instance, and they have an existing lot,
I don't look at the lot size. That lot was created
under
previous
regulations or what have you.
Having said that,
it does read, I mean, regulations do read
to cover lot size.
Go ahead.
Okay.
>> Okay, if I understand that correctly,
if it does
get denied,
they don't have to
The Zoning Board of Appeals does not have to meet with me for six months. Is that correct? No,
>> not at all. I probably shouldn't have gotten into that. If no,
ZABA would hear your application immediately.
Just, they have the right not to listen to it to
a reapplication
for six months, but you haven't applied to them as yet.
Okay, yep.
Probably shouldn't have got into that.
No, it's okay. To clarify.
I have one quick question.
Go ahead, Kevin.
>> So
are the garage and the accessory apartment considered two separate line items on the application?
Yeah.
>> So the garage is considered to be part of the accessory apartment.
At this note, this was more for just clarification on my end. Just was looking at it The
>> application doesn't really differentiate,
but but as
far as
the the
accessory department would be defined by the the finished space.
The square footage that I would requirements
would apply to
the finished space, the living space, the habitable space.
>> Because the
When I was looking at the rags and maybe I'm wrong, but
accessory department was calling out gross area.
And the gross area was anything that was.
I don't know they had a there was a thing in there that said, if it was more than half of the structure was showing above grade,
then that was considered in gross area.
So I was just curious,
just for reference, if
the garage is just someone putting an addition on their house and the accessory apartment is another thing, or
if
the entire unit that's being added on is the accessory apartment?
>> Well, it's not clear, Kevin. I think that the accessory apartment is the accessory apartment and the garage,
at least what we did on a previous application,
is we allowed the garage space
to contribute to the
gross
square footage.
And
in fact,
on the last one,
the applicant needed,
I think, the gross square footage of garage
to give him enough so that he could go to the maximum
800 square foot
being the right percentage of that.
So it is kind of interesting that the applicant,
I think, could put up a three car garage
without coming to us,
but the accessory apartment
on top of it
at this point we're
>> Right, because
the room on top
is at the maximum area
and then when you include the garage on the bottom, you
way exceed the 33%
allotment for
additional capacity over the gross square footage of the house that already exists.
>> Yes,
I did not consider the garage square footage
to be part of the accessory accessory apartment.
>> Okay, that was what I was wondering. You could be wrong on that. Yeah, was just wondering for clarification.
>> Question. Yeah, I
assumed that
it wasn't part of the equation,
but
I could be mistaken.
>> So
I have a question then.
Can somebody who's.
Go ahead. But he wants to build a garage.
All they need is to have their plans to get a building permit. They don't need to be approved by
us or P and Z.
I mean the
VBA.
>> Is that correct? As long as they meet the setback requirements,
you know, for the lot and
in all those other things. Yes. Okay.
>> Yeah, that's basically what I was wondering too. Thanks, Ann. Yep.
>> It is. So if he puts in a garage,
he can put in a garage.
If he wants the accessory upstairs
in the garage,
he needs to
a permit for that from us. Any
other questions?
And that's all good discussion. You never get into the sticky points of an application
until you're right on the verge of
whether or not you meet the requirements. When you exceed the requirements by a lot, the discussion's always very easy.
So at this point,
I would
does somebody want to make a motion
to approve
the application?
And the reason
I
say approve as opposed to a motion to disapprove,
again if we make a motion to disapprove an application and the motion
fails,
I don't know where that puts us.
So
we always go to the positive, make a motion to approve it,
and then if it's denied,
we know where we stand.
>> I move that we approve
the,
the application for an accessory apartment
at 128 Wheeling Road.
>> Thank you. Is
there a second? I'll second then. Thank you, Scott.
Any further discussion on the application?
Hearing none, I'll call for a vote.
Anne?
I'd
like to say aye.
Scott? No.
Leanne?
No.
Steve?
Sorry, I was on mute. No.
>> And I vote
no as well.
The application is denied by a vote of
four-one-zero.
And to Adam, when you go to the zoning board of appeals,
I recommend you
include the discussion about the fact you can build the garage
and maybe they would be sympathetic to why can't you put the accessory department
up there.
If they don't agree, come back
in less than a year we should have the matter resolved and I think we will be
more lenient.
Certainly
my vote
against
has got nothing to do with the project you want to do. It's not an
to meet our regulations as they are currently written.
And
I like what you're trying to do.
>> Okay. Yeah. I appreciate that. Thank you.
Who would I follow-up with about the joining board of appeals? I know there's an application online. I've already printed out.
But I would send that into just the town hall with the tech as well.
>> You should discuss
that with agent Halsey
who, you know, the ZBA,
you know, he is the
agent for the ZBA as well. So
in this case we've made that easy for you.
Thank you.
Okay, I'm going to move on to old business 5C.
Request of Christopher Bell, agent for William Joe Genovese applicant seeking an extension of existing special permit to operate sand gravel pit at 517 Route 6.
That's section 16 of the Andover Zoning Regulations.
We've had the
I guess the real reason that
I added this
to the agenda tonight because we did in fact
authorize
the approval at the last meeting,
there was a question as to whether or not
there was a cease and desist from planning and zoning.
There was a cease and desist letter
issued.
It went to the
property owner,
not the owner's engineer. That's why Chris Bell, as of the last meeting,
did not
seen that.
Also,
Jim was our agent was not at the last meeting and I wanted to,
know, he's been a little bit tied up and I know we have not issued
the notice of approval
in a timely
manner to get that done and so with
those couple of loose ends, I wanted to put this on the agenda again for discussion tonight so that we could get an update from
agent Halsey on where we actually stand on that
and make sure that all our questions
>> All right. Yes, the cease and desist was sent to Bill Genovese, who is the applicant of record. I sent it to him at the address,
his business address, because
that was the address on the application.
Whether he received it or not, don't know.
But my plan was to have them file a special
permit for the original approval
is filed on the land records. So I was having them file an extension
in
a similar fashion,
along with just a letter saying that the peace and desist is hereby lifted.
And when they file that document,
it's a one page document in the land records
that would effectively
negate the cease and desist.
As far as I'm concerned, that's the appropriate
approach.
On the second matter, I know that there was an issue about the detention pond.
Applicant wanted to to
grade that over, I believe.
And I did get
written correspondence from the town engineer Brandon Hanfield.
I saw it today and I sent it for posting
late or early this evening.
It will get posted when
when Amanda who who does her postings is in the office next ensuing
And he was in concurrence that he thought it would be a good idea. There was no need to retain that pond for
as far as protection of the site, and that it would
be
said would be
in a better
situation for development and marketing without
that pond.
Am I still on? Yes.
Thank you.
>> I think everybody's just trying to take in all this because this is late breaking
news.
>> If I may, Mr. Chairman?
Go ahead. Yep. My name is Chris Bell, a professional engineer representing
the applicant.
Just to back up a couple of steps.
As you recall,
you gave me four items,
bullet items to take care of by the next meeting.
Number one is to
report every week to Jim House. You give him a written report of an update of the gravel pit of any outstanding items
and any new items that may have arose,
which I have done every week.
We had to
get the grass
that's on the very top of the mound that
we couldn't see from below, but you can see from a much higher elevation. That finally got done. We were really delayed by the amount of rain that we had
because after it rain, we had to wait till it dried out so we wouldn't get the truck wouldn't get stuck in there. But it finally got done
just over a week ago, I guess, about two weeks ago.
We did get blocks to block the
turtle nesting area. There were some on-site which they
put up
about a week after the last meeting.
And there are additional blocks that we had ordered,
which aren't really necessary to block anymore. Mean, the two blocks do a pretty good job. You can't really drive through that area.
But we're gonna put a couple additional blocks up
there. And also, we have some that are gonna be used for the front driveway once the
gravel pit closes, we're gonna block off that driveway.
So that's why we we have quite a few on-site.
The last item
was the item regarding the detention pond.
Member Scott
Persons asked
us to
to look into the matter.
This was
a suggestion by John Valenti a couple years ago to leave it there,
which I
wasn't for or against at the time. But
as we thought about it, we think it should be filled
for a number of reasons.
First of all, it's gonna be a a liability for the owner. He's gonna have to grade it, seat it,
most likely put a fence around it. I would suggest putting a fence around it. And,
and it's not the most ideal place for a a detention pond, and it's
a little bit oversized
for what,
a site might be using.
This
afternoon,
the town engineer, Brandon,
>> sent a letter. I don't know if everyone's read the letter or not.
I think they have not. That was the letter that you talked about
>> previously.
Mr. Chairman,
with your permission,
I can put that up on the screen. With permission,
can share my screen if you want to read it. Okay.
Yep. Go ahead, Chris.
>> I
think it's going to try to take up too much of the space here.
Hold on.
I'm told that it's on. Did everybody see Yep.
>> Did you see it? Yes. Okay.
We'll
give everybody a couple minutes to read through it there.
Okay. I think everybody's had a chance to take a look at that.
And again, I apologize for not getting that posted
so that everybody could see it before we came to meeting tonight.
But
as I see it,
the Commission tonight
can
our job tonight is to consider whether or not we should modify
the existing restoration
plan
to remove the requirement to maintain the detention
basin
based on the recommendation
of the applicant's engineer
and
our engineer.
Is that going to be a motion, Jed? That
>> will be a motion. Now that I've explained what it is that we're trying to do, I am going to
ask somebody to make a motion to do just that.
Could I add a note, Mr. Chairman?
A comment?
Yes.
>> With your permission.
I can,
we can have this inclusive as part of the
as built because we have to do an as built
for
the project as part of the final restoration.
When the restoration is done, we have to do a grading plan
to show that we're at grade.
And
I mean, can just have this as an order to
close the tension pond.
And
I guess what I
would need to ask is
normally we would take everything out, the pipe and everything else.
We wouldn't wanna leave that there,
But we would put it back, know, have the whole grading plan done
like that. I mean, don't wanna have to go back and forth with the commission with this. I mean, would you agree we should take everything out and basically,
you know, the whole site is going be silk fenced
and it'll
be up to someone else's
job to
design the site plan and detention basin.
You know, it's not going to have an increase in runoff because of all the grass. I mean, this was,
you know, really bare ground
like a meadow before. It's
>> No, I understand. And my
goal tonight was to just get the motion
into our minutes
and then between agent Halsey and
our engineer and you, you can work through the details of does the pipe stay or go.
But we will authorize
changing the plan
To remove it.
>> Remove the detention
basin as part of the restoration.
Okay. So that, you know, I was I
think all of us were
unhappy when we found out how much of the original plan we weren't doing.
And
so I would like to have it clear what we're changing in the plan so that when
you do your final wrap up report,
there's justification
for all that we've got there.
Okay.
Thank you.
>> So I think we had Scott made a motion.
And I don't know that we had a second to the motion.
I'll second it. Okay.
>> Thank you, Anne.
Any discussion by the Commission
on the motion?
>> Yes, this is Leanne. I have two or three questions. Go ahead.
So this motion is strictly about the detention basin?
Yes.
>> Okay, so have the to be clear because as you said we did get some items some information just tonight. Have the other three items from last month's minutes been fulfilled
and has the zoning agent seen them?
>> That
was yes. The answer to the question is yes. And that was
the discussion that Chris Bell had just a minute ago where he talked about
the letter that he sent to Jim dated July 16.
And I think that one is posted online.
But it only
got posted today. So if you missed
it,
that's understandable. But it says the special seed for the turtle area is still on order.
Concrete blocks were installed to protect the turtle nest area.
Bear area on top of the back hill was hydro seeded last Saturday.
There was no removal of material this week and he sent all the information to Brandon,
which we did look at the letter that Brandon sent back in response to that recommending removal of the detention base.
So the other items that we had talked about
at the last meeting have all been addressed.
>> Okay.
And that includes the item that says submit weekly reports to the zoning agent on the status of the project?
>> Yes. That was not addressed
specifically
in the letter,
Chris Bell did say that he had been reporting
to
>> agent Halsey on a weekly basis. And to the best of my knowledge, posted
each of those
>> reports. Okay, I didn't see them. I didn't know there was anything in addition to what we were sent
as,
Travelers. But if you're stipulating that it's there, then okay. And my other question is,
I guess I'm a little confused about the cease and desist part.
If
mister Genovese was sent a cease and desist
letter to the address on file,
but I as I understand it, mister Bell said tonight that and and last month that he didn't know about it, and I think the chairman also was
a little up in the air about whether or it had been issued in the first place. Is that right, Jed?
>> That is correct. I knew
I had seen the letter that Jim wrote because he had it vetted through
Mark Branch,
our attorney.
So I knew the letter existed.
Who specifically
it got mailed to was the part that I was unclear of.
Jim's unavailability
leading up to the last meeting
didn't give me a chance to chase that down. I don't believe I posted that
>> letter until such time as it was brought to my attention that there was some confusion.
>> Do we not send things by certified mail or registered mail or something that requires a signature
for something like this? We do.
>> Yeah, I know we didn't get anything bad. Did you send a cease and desist by certified
mail? Yes, definitely.
>> This And was so nothing was received back by the town?
I don't believe so, no.
>> The applicant recalls, and I recall the cease and desist from wetlands, and that's
the one we were
really concentrating on to get done right away.
I never saw the cease and desist for planning and zoning, but as we worked through the wetlands one, by the time that was done,
well, we were okay with
the items, I guess, on the cease and desist for the planning and zoning.
But
the applicant doesn't recall seeing that either.
But he did get the one from Wetlands, so I saw also.
>> So I'm gonna assume that the address on file
that we had is the same that the Wetlands Commission had.
I wouldn't assume that at all.
I don't know. You wouldn't assume that? No.
>> I know that the Wetlands agent had an issue with
a document that went to Mr. Genovese in the past.
What kind of issue? Quite honestly,
if somebody doesn't pick up a certified letter,
it's not really my concern.
That's what I've been told to
I mean, quite frankly, I didn't care because I was working with
the applicant and
his engineer
to address the problem, the issues that were were cited.
So it was
I assumed he had gotten it, but
I don't know.
>> I'll tell you something from being up in his business
in New Britain. He gets a lot of certified letters every day,
and
it doesn't surprise me if this just went
past his desk and,
you know,
maybe he never saw it.
Right? He did see the wetlands one because we're
you know, we all talked about it.
But if you didn't get a receipt back,
then he didn't get it. Or he didn't.
>> If you didn't get a receipt back, then he can get it. Is that you
>> know? No, that doesn't mean anything that well, yes, it means it doesn't mean that
a lot of people choose not to pick up their certified mail. Right. They didn't sign. He didn't sign for it. They didn't get a receipt that. Right. I don't know where it went. That
>> will go right back to you immediately.
It doesn't,
from what I remember,
when someone doesn't sign a certified
letter, it goes right back to the person that sent it with a note saying, guess what, they didn't sign it or they didn't accept it. Right. It doesn't hang around anymore,
it doesn't get lost.
Hopefully not. It goes back to whoever sent it. Right.
>> This is Leanne again.
I'm sorry, somebody else
still finishing?
Nope. Come in Leanne.
>> I I don't as long as the other
conditions the other three conditions from last month's minutes are okay and the you know the zoning agent wasn't available last month.
The people are in agreement about the detention basin tonight
but I would like for the record to say I don't think it should be our problem
if somebody doesn't
either
open their certified mail, send it back, whatever you're supposed to do, because that's the whole point of certified mail. And a cease and desist is a big deal.
And I just would like to say for the record that I don't think it should be our problem that we didn't get it back and I think I'm going to respectfully disagree with Jim that
it should have been looked out for if that's the term on the town's end whether it was him or I'm not sure what the arrangement is right now.
We used to have a full time administrative assistant. We know we don't have one anymore in the building department and that's been in flux with cross training, but I just think it's important to
note that
>> nobody else would happen to it. Leah, I'm in agreement. It's once we send it out,
it's a done deal.
>> Are you saying that we have a record of it? It's we do have a defense if that's the right word if we don't get anything back? Yeah.
So we do have a record of sending it and then yes.
So you're saying that is
if I understand what you're saying that's sufficient to
show that the town did their part? Yes.
>> If if we had to move forward with with civil action,
that would have sufficed in court. That's the that's the advice that I've gotten
in the past from Mark Brantz.
>> Okay. Well, that's fine then. It it just sounds a little funny that it it you know, the explanation tonight, the way I heard it was that anybody can either ignore anything on purpose or if they genuinely don't get it, but the fact remains that the town
never heard back. But if you're saying that
as long as we can document what we did, then that holds up, then I guess that's satisfactory to me. Yeah. It's possible that that something came back indicating
>> that he didn't, you know, that it wasn't picked up. I don't know. I don't know the answer to that. I I do know that I have a record of mailing it. That's all. That's all I can say. If we have a record of Okay. Well, thank you for that. Keep a receipt, and that's got the tracking number, you should be able to look it up. Yes, we have it.
>> Thank you. Yep, and I will
I share Leanne's
concern
that it is a big deal. I guess
the matter in mitigation in this particular case was
Jim and I both knew that
all work at the gravel pit was
stopped.
And so it appeared to us like the letter had been received.
We'll do a better job of tracking that stuff going forward a little bit because
it
was our goal to get it stopped and it did get stopped. But we ought to
if it hadn't, and we hadn't been tracking that, if
it hadn't stopped and then we were talking about it a month later, that would have
not been a good situation. So
I guess that's the only blemish I see on what I thought was a very successful
remediation
and renewal
of the gravel pit application.
>> Quite frankly, I had numerous,
I had
a lot of conversations with
Chris Bell
on the matter and met him
and other parties on-site,
you know,
and I wasn't concerned about the
issues
were being taken care of. I
wasn't overly concerned about whether
somebody received the cease and desist.
>> But we
should because at some point in time,
the cease and desist won't have ceased. And then we'll be trying to figure out why that and something
untoward could
happen then. So
we'll
look at that a little bit. We certainly did our part from the town, but it would be nice to know that the guy got the letter that we took such pains to send to him with tracking system on it.
Okay, well that's all I got. All that I'd like, yeah, I think we've covered enough the
ability to mail at this point.
We'll do better.
>> Jim, what stage
that,
what stage will the detention pond leave?
It's towards the end of the project.
>> Was that written anywhere? When when are they gonna fill it, pull the pipe and all that? Well, would be part of the final phase, I believe.
>> I mean, saying that based on memory,
I don't have a plan in front of me. Don't I can't square that case, but that
>> would certainly make sense to me. Chris, do you have when do you think?
>> My understanding
was the tension pod is going to be there
until we final grade the site
and
have enough material to fill it
and have grass growing
and then we basically,
that's the last thing we do is fill the pond
topsoil seed that
and that's it. That's not the last thing we do
Presenting tincture pond should stay there until
>> we're really done with the grading operation. That's going to be the last thing before you drive out of there. That's correct. Yeah, sorry. Missed that
>> one through. I mean, it's on the plan.
It's shown to stay there. Now we're now we're discussing
eliminating.
>> I mean, this is why we put it where we put it,
because we wanted to be close by to the end of the operation.
We went back and forth where we were gonna start the project
initially.
We were gonna start in the front, but it works best for the pond to be there if you start in the front. It works best if the pond is there if you start in the middle. And that's why we started in the middle. So we said, we'll just leave it there, put a channel to it,
and
that'll be the last place
for us to be as far as braiding goes.
>> Another question I have is I recall that they were supposed to put stones
around the turtle
area.
>> Oh,
we had a discussion the next day.
Yeah, you're correct.
We talked about large stones.
And I called Jim the next day when I told the owner, he had to put large stones, he said.
Very
bluntly, he goes, I don't really have any of those. I don't like large stones.
Have some concrete blocks,
wouldn't that be better?
I said, well, they're bigger than what we needed.
And I asked him about that and I asked the town engineer and they
both didn't seem to have any objection to that.
They can definitely be a lot easier moved
with a forklift than the rocks could.
So I was,
I didn't get any opposition with that, I didn't want to have to wait to come back to the Commission to ask them again and miss the date of being, having not done for two weeks, so we we put those concrete blocks up right away.
I I hope that the Commission wasn't dead set on having large stones.
But again, it is your choice.
I hope that you have on that, Scott?
>> Excuse me. Did you have a concern about the concrete blocks versus stones?
>> I think that the turtles are probably like the stones better
to
be honest with you.
>> They're a bigger
than the turtles. Don't know if they
>> Yeah, it could be imposing to the turtles.
I don't know.
I would say I'm suggesting It
>> always comes down to what the commission says and then when we get to the field people change things.
>> Well, suggest you put less blocks up and put, you know,
tree, you know, like a white oak log across it, it would look nice and he didn't like that either.
So this is what I, this is what we got.
But it's up to the commission.
>> Well, do we have something that says stones are required or you know I thought that came up as a comment during Yeah, Chris Bell said that he was gonna get them off his property.
Yeah, that didn't happen either.
>> Well, we were gonna get the concrete blocks off the property? No, stones. Stones. Stones.
>> Also the
the detention basin originally was supposed to be moved at every stage of the project.
>> That
wasn't actually part of the conditions, that was a suggestion. That
>> was, yeah, that was, I recall that. Yeah, I do recall that, but
I
There's
>> a lot of things that have changed,
but I don't have any problem. If everybody else is all right with the concrete blocks, I'm all right with them.
If I had my druthers, I would put stones in.
>> Okay.
I would tend to agree with that, but
I was outvoted.
>> Well,
on
Agent Halsey and our engineer
thinking that that was okay,
I think
that
that should be okay. And if
you want that in the motion, we can put that in the motion. But I
know the
item that we were supposed to be coming back to discuss was in fact the detention basin and
that's where I'm at.
So I think we have a motion
on the floor
to delete the requirement to maintain the detention basin
as part of the restoration plan.
And
I think we had a second to that motion. Is that correct, Mindy?
>> Yes, I had a second. We just didn't vote on it. Okay, so now we've
>> had any other discussion on that before we vote?
Hearing none, I'll call for a vote. Anne?
Aye.
Scott?
Leanne?
Aye.
>> Steve?
I vote aye as well.
The motion passes five
zero zero.
>> Okay, thank you.
And I assume Mr. Chairman that you'll still be looking for a report every week from me? That's correct.
>> Unless agent Halsey comes to us and says, nope, I'm tired of getting that all those emails once a month. I
like having the report before
the meeting and update.
Jim, you have any flavor for whether you think weekly or monthly is better for you?
>> Weekly, I like weekly. Okay. I I don't think it's a tremendous amount of work for Let's stick with weekly. Well,
>> if nothing's going on, there's not a lot of work to do. Will try to get it on a Thursday morning
so that you can get it posted.
I waited
a lot of times till Friday because I was waiting to get something from somebody and
you know, when I don't get it,
gotta put the letter out anyway.
And I was hoping to get something done.
I'll make I'll try to make sure it's done at least about every Thursday. Again, nothing's been happening there. The owner says, you you're going to get everything done before you start moving stuff again.
So now that we've got everything resolved,
they're ready to go again.
>> Okay, well, correct me if I'm wrong, Jim, but we need to wait two weeks following
do we need to wait two weeks following the issuance
of the letter in the newspaper
to allow anybody to
complain. I don't know what the technicality is there. But in this case, since it's a renewal versus
you know, approval of an application,
do we need to wait two weeks at this point or is the
applicant good to go?
>> I don't see any reason
to hold
them up.
Okay. It's valid, still revoke as far as I'm concerned.
>> And
Chris, I think based on that and the fact that this is a permit renewal,
I agree that you're good to go and start moving material
from the gravel bit again. I think
all of us want to see it wrapped up sooner rather than later. Absolutely.
>> I'll be watching a closer eye on this and as soon as we get to the point when we're,
you know, an area
has agreed to, you know, less than
two phases, you know, like a phase and a half, which is only going to be another,
maybe
once he takes that big mound that's out there and some of the bank, it's not going to be too long until we have to do another,
know, bring the restoration up to the next
point again, you know, go up another 100 feet.
We'll be watching them. Okay.
Thank you, Chris. Thank you.
Thank you, everyone.
Thanks, Chris. Next
>> item on the agenda is
discussion possible action previously approved special permit for previously approved kennel at 241 Route 6. And
we talked about this a little bit last time. I went out and did some more research as did Jim following that.
And while
it is clear to me that
the permit was approved
by the Commission
and we have the permit,
the underlying
documentation
that should have gone in
like a site plan
to
support the application so that we
here know what would be approved
is missing.
We
have not been able to find
that.
So I don't know, I know the special permit was approved, but I don't know
what they approved.
And so on
trying to figure out the way ahead getting with
Agent Halsey
today there's,
I think we use the term permit modification.
Yes. And
based on the fact that
there have been
no complaints
about the kennel operation
having gone on in
the past numerous years that it has been in existence.
You know, there's words in our regulations that would allow us to if we've already gone and held a public hearing and this this permit is going to be very similar to what was approved in the past.
We don't have to do that again and we can just process
a modified
application so that we can discuss what it is that the applicant is really doing,
where he's doing,
and then we can compare that to our regulations and make sure that
it meets
what the regulations require.
Is that acceptable to you, Mr. Beebe?
>> Yep. Yeah, I talked with Jim today. He said he would help me get that together for you guys.
Yep. So yeah.
And
I
>> know the original
plan and everything like that. I mean, I don't have it with me, but the main thing, and I may be able to find it, was originally it was a huge commercial kennel.
And right now it's just fencing
in a field
and use of some of the existing, like a heifer barn that was on the farm previously.
So I never went and built the elaborate building and kennel runs and all that.
So that's what the original plan is.
Right now, and Jim's been there and some
other people know about it. I mean, you can Google Earth
It's it's
just fencing in a field off of a heifer barn
and some kennels that you would buy a tractor supply
to house the dogs during the day. And then I have a
have a bus that holds 17 crates that we go on field trips and things like that.
And I just want the board to know like this all came about because I bought my partner out
and the state wants to inspect
the facility,
I already had them come in and inspect it so I would know when I pass what I have to do and I don't have to do anything.
But the funny part in all this matter is if I park my bus at the commuter lot and load my clients,
I'm not breaking any laws.
But if I'm at the farm and I have it there, they want me to have all these
Where actually it's safer for everybody on a 200 acre farm.
It's kind of nonsense. And
>> so one of the things
I asked you last time, why is it that if you've got a training
facility
where we're asking to put a kennel in and for
everybody else, this is section 19 of our
>> So hold on, hold on. You asked
if I was putting in a kennel and the answer right now is no. Down the road someday maybe.
The landowner is Serenity Post. She said if I ever want to put in a kennel but right now I'm not looking, I'm at the end of my career.
You know, I'm 50 years old. I'm looking for ten more years to train dogs in a field and on my merry way of retirement.
I'm not looking to build any facility.
It's
all existing buildings on the property.
>> And
as long as
those indoor housing facilities comply with state regulations for commercial
>> And that's what this is all about for Jim to sign a paper
for the state of Connecticut to go there and say whether or not I'm
meeting regulations.
>> Okay, so you're saying that you do meet that requirement?
>> Yes, because I had them. So listen, I'm also the town of Andover ACO.
So I've been dealing with the state of Connecticut in some form or another in the ag business
for the last twenty five years. So I have a good relationship with them. So I already asked them to come and inspect me so that when I got this paper signed,
if there was a problem, could already have it addressed,
right?
The only real glitch in that whole thing is the boarding
and that's because of the dogs coming during the day and staying more than five hours. That
in the state classifies me as a boarding facility,
even though I'm not a boarding facility.
They had nowhere to put it in their licensing years ago. So that's where it falls.
Okay,
>> I just don't want to approve a permit and then the state comes back and says what a bunch of yo yos you guys are. No, no, no.
Jimmy: So
if you put in an application then,
other question
I have for you is I saw that on the little outline map that we have posted,
you have to be very close if not within the flood prone district.
>> So I don't know where that is. I talked to Jim,
but I seriously doubt I'm within the flood zone District because He's not in the. Yeah, Scott knows the property better than I do. Okay.
And
I mean, I'm next to the cemetery, so you allowed him to bury people there. So I doubt him in a flood zone.
>> Okay, good enough. I went to
our zoning map that has the flood Prone District
on it. And I see that it's over there by
Pine Ridge Drive.
>> Oh, I'm not over there.
Well,
map I mean, I know it's there, but I mean, Scott can tell you. Okay. He owns that land better than anybody. Yep, I'm there. That's why we're talking about it tonight.
>> Because when I looked at the map you provided,
it looked like it
was drawn
within the flood Prone District.
Okay. And
regulations say you can't do that. Right.
That doesn't mean that you say you've got 200 acres over there you're using for a kennel,
that maybe
a small portion of that in the flood prone district,
I don't really care.
But the majority of your kennel area
shouldn't be
where it's going to flood.
>> Right, and what I'm telling you is I don't have a kennel area, right? I use the Heifer Barn that's been there. It's just a concrete slab.
And then there's just
like
you would buy a tractor supply
sitting on the ground on P stone.
I'm
not building any buildings I guess is what I'm saying.
The only thing I'm using is where you've already approved these buildings before where there were 60 cows at one time.
Scott, can you explain better than I can? I mean, you know the land.
>> I
would like to just know what Jed wants and the Commission needs to know before they okay it.
Just know it's not in the flood zone, Jed. Okay,
>> and that's good to know.
The map that we provide on where the kennel is operating
ought to reflect that.
What can
tell you that I did was I looked through our regulations on kennels
and tried to answer the question, are we in compliance with those? And I could not do that. Exactly. None of the other commission members can either. It's every
>> different type of panel or the usages,
everyone goes back to camping in the flood prone district.
The
elevation jet is at the same elevation as
house
that's down there. Okay,
>> yep. But it would be nice if the application
addressed
what the requirements are and
we can
make a decision based on our regulations.
>> It should say something about what type are
we going to have here too.
>> It's presently a type C, which is a commercial kennel. Commercial kennel, yeah. Yeah.
I
wasn't
here when you got the original,
We went through the process initially, but I mean, don't have any problem handling training grooming showing.
To certainly fall under this the definition of kennel here. Don't. Right.
The
fact that they may not spend the night there
is not a particular concern to me.
Seems like the right approach. I mean, the way it was handled
initially and modification
could just address what's what is there now. And with with the approval of the commission, and I'd be happy to transpose
that flood zone. Mean, I did, you know, when I met with Scott out there, we did discuss the flood zone. I didn't have the flood zone. I didn't have the map and hit my hand but we got a big idea as to where it was. It's it seems to be a distance from from any any activity that's that's going on there.
>> Okay.
So
the request for the commission at this point,
I think is to
have a motion
that asks
the applicant
to provide a modified
application
for our approval.
Okay,
so
>> Again,
you're much
more familiar
with this stuff than I am, but I read words
that
Thanks.
No kennel will be so located or allowed to fall into such state of repairs to constitute NYSOR either to the adjacent property owners or to the general public.
Right.
>> So
my whole thing here is I don't have a building.
Right? So as much as they want me to be under the commercial kennel, it's because the dogs stay for more than four hours.
>> Well, and does that mean that you have to make it so the dogs don't stay more than four hours so that you could be in compliance with the regulations?
>> No, it's not that I'm not in compliance with any regulations. The point is, I don't have a building.
Right? So what the state is saying is, all I need is the town to sign that one piece of paper that says, I have approval,
Praying dogs there, and they can be there.
And then they take all the regulations that apply
from the Department of Agriculture,
no different than the dog pound or any other
farm, And then they come in and inspect.
Like the inspections do for the town pound, she'd go from there
three driveways up and then inspect my place.
That's like a commercial kitchen in a restaurant.
And
so, I mean, I would agree. I agree that if it's an eyesore, I have to keep it up.
>> I don't see anything here yet.
I mean highest classification it's 10 acres you have to have over 10 acres. He's on 200
probably a thousand
maybe not a thousand feet but he's
you know 700
feet from the closest
home.
And
it's at the elevation of the home that's down there that Scott's mother lives in so. Okay.
>> I know that this is an area that is probably not black and white. Our
job
is to receive an application
from an applicant that shows how they meet the regulations
and then we vote on whether or not it meets regulations.
Don't have any of that. Have meeting minutes that say a previous
special permit was approved.
We don't know what was approved. We don't know what the conditions of approval were.
And so I'm looking for that information
so we can make an assessment.
Does
that make sense?
>> We need a motion to provide a modified application
to the zoning agent for approval.
This is Leanne. I think that's reasonable.
>> You. Leanne, you were there for all of Leanne was there through all of it. Leanne, like she was there the whole time.
>> I know Susan England was as well,
but she's not here tonight.
But that's what I'm looking for is to
tell the story of what we actually have. We asked to build a kennel that we didn't build.
I'm told it's in a different spot from what was approved.
And I can't find anything that talks about what was actually approved.
And so I need a little bit more so the commission can vote on it in good conscience.
>> Are we doing what makes sense? Now that was the motion that I just gave you, Ted. Okay. Read it again, Scott Lee. Motion to provide modified application
to the zoning agent
for approval.
>> And would that be
are you suggesting that it doesn't need to come back to planning and zoning?
>> As
long as it
fits with the regulations,
as long as it fits with the regulation.
I think Who would it go to?
>> If
it's going to be a class
Charlie Kennel,
it's got to come back to the commission.
Commercial
class?
Yes.
>> For approval, then we'll change it to for approval by planning and zoning. Okay.
So motion to provide a modified
application to the zoning agent for approval by planning and zoning.
Is
there a second to that motion?
I'll second. This is Leanne. Thank you, Leanne.
Any other discussion?
>> And that's what you're looking for is
something on paper that said that he
fulfills all the regulation requirements.
Yes.
And some good
maps showing that it's out of the flood zone.
How far it is from adjacent neighbors?
>> It talks about a fence in there. It'd be nice It's if you have to show the
going to be fenced in.
Perfect.
Okay
any other discussion?
>> So just to this is Leanne just to be clear Mr.
Beebe isn't saying
that he's going to establish a kennel
now. He wants
and needs from the state
something from the town
that approves what he's doing now. Is that in a nutshell? I know we talked about flood zone and neighbors
and things like that.
That's right. I know in a nutshell isn't a technical term, but
>> That's my interest. He's not building a structure, but he's operating a kennel. He's operating the
training facility,
which falls under commercial kennel.
>> And is that because of the number of hours right there that the dogs are on the premises?
Yes,
that's a state regulation that.
Okay, I'm dealing with my thought of local regulation.
>> I mean, all all
I'm trying to do is to get the applicant
to come up with a I mean, the idea is to come up with a plan
showing what's there now or
poses to do
treat it as a modification to the existing
permit that was approved.
That was never Okay. That sounds
>> if we get something, as Jed said, if we get something just like that, it sounds like it would be helpful to us and the applicant
to show what's going on. Yeah.
Applicant also.
>> Any other discussion?
Hearing none, call for a vote. Anne?
Aye.
>> Scott? Aye.
Leanne?
Aye.
Steve?
I vote aye as well. Motion passes five zero zero.
Moving on.
Affordable housing plan and recent
legislation.
So
Mindy, if you can allow me to share my screen, I will go through what I've got on that
tonight.
Should be able to. Yep. Thank you.
>> Okay. So
not
a smooth
PowerPoint.
Oh,
this fireworks are going off.
Must be time to close the meeting.
Me go shut my door and maybe it'll keep some of that noise out of here.
Is
the
location of the presentation such that anybody
can see it well? For me, I've got all the pictures over on the right hand side and it's blocking out the edge of the presentation.
How
about that? Okay. We'll try that.
So anyhow,
last at
meeting we talked about the fact that we submitted
a request
to the state for a grant to do our affordable housing plan.
And that is it.
Since then, and we have not heard back whether or not grant approved or not, I assume that it will be.
But we have put out
a request for,
I put RFP request for proposal,
request for quote, whatever,
request for bid for the different planners around the state
to
come in that want to help us build our affordable housing plan.
And we issued that on July 15. And so just on the big
scheme of things, what we're looking at on this,
want the bids are due back
to Eric
on the September 1.
We're going to look to award the contract on the October 1,
hold an initial public hearing in November on development
of the plan,
Work on the plan over the course of the winter. In April, hold the public hearing on the proposed plan
so in May we can approve it and submit it to the state. So that's a big picture
on affordable housing plan, what we've got there.
In
the information
for this is what I sent out to everybody a link. Steve, I don't recall whether or not I sent it to you, but there was a link from Halloran Sage that
talked about all the legislative changes and
lots of words in that. And I'm trying to figure out what the actions are so I can hold me to making sure that we get the actions done in time.
So if I didn't send that to you, Steve, let me know and I'll try it again.
>> Yeah, I don't think I saw it, Jed, but I'll check my inbox again. Okay,
>> yep. And very well could be
that I missed you on that. It was a while ago that that went out.
One
of the things that is in the legislation that changed a lot is on accessory apartments.
And
these
changes for accessory apartments will be effective
01/01/2022.
And it's a little confusing to me how it works, but we can,
I guess in January 2022 is when they can be effective?
If we choose as a commission to opt out of those requirements, we have to do that by 01/01/2023.
I would have thought that we would have had to opt out before they went into effect,
but that's not what I see there.
But on 01/01/2023,
unless we opt out, any non compliant existing regs
with respect to these updates
become null and void, which essentially gives
any property owner
the right
to build an accessory apartment on any authorized
lot.
We might not want that.
We might not want that. Maybe out in the ARD we don't want that for a 40,000 square foot lot. In
the lake zone, it requires 120,000.
>> Yep, and the lake zone requires 120,000
because we've got some lots in the lake zone
that are maybe an eighth of an acre.
I think I've seen 8,000 square feet for
lot size.
Certainly with the problems of septic
design and all that stuff in the lake zone,
we do want something different.
So what I plan to do is when we get this
smart planner guy to help us build the affordable housing plan,
since accessory apartments are a key element of that,
he can lead the discussion through a discussion on that and we can figure out what it is that we want to do.
But I was not willing to commit to our applicant tonight to have that done in the very near future because there are a lot of changes coming on with respect to planning and zoning.
I think we're going to struggle, I'm going to struggle to do this. Now if there's somebody out there
on the Commission that wants to assist in developing proposed changes,
that has legal backgrounds and that sort of thing, and I'm all in favor of any assistance
that might come my way on any of that.
But I think other
than that, you know, this can be part of what the planner is helping to guide us through.
So that's going to be a big change. If we do nothing, everybody's
got a chance to put in an
accessory apartment. I think it authorizes, we limit it to 800 square feet. The new state regs would propose that we go up to 1,000 square feet for the accessory apartment.
Jimmy: New requirement for Commission training.
Jimmy:
I got to be the chairman of the planning and zoning Commission without any training whatsoever
and it did not feel good. And
so I do think that
it's
good that we all get to do some training and it's not an immediate problem
for us but it says after
January 20,
01/01/2023
each member shall get four hours of training by the next year.
And we're going to do training every other year thereafter.
So it's four
hours every other year.
I
know that we have
a hard time getting people to
want to be on the commissions because everybody's overextended.
But
I think
you would all find this beneficial. The people that have gone to the various trainings we've held, I think have all thought that it was very worthwhile.
So
that'll be coming and I encourage you all to do the training that's available to us starting as soon as the next one comes around. I've been to several
and I thought they were all very worthwhile.
And I need to report compliance annually to the Board of Selectmen on how we're doing on that. So
that'll be a part of our deal.
Then I put a slide in here on other stuff and
a couple other things that
you know as of the July 1 of this year,
we are required to resume posting
our
decisions
and our public hearings and all that in the local newspaper.
Was
eliminated as a requirement due to the pandemic.
I think those rules
have expired on the end of June.
And so now we are encouraged to continue electronic posting,
but we need to go back to the
posting in the River East as well.
I like seeing those things in there.
That's how I learn a lot about what's going on in the town.
04/01/2022,
there's permanently
updated regulations on outdoor dining. And
again, as I looked through it, they were kind of confusing to me. Didn't know exactly what they said.
Jim hasn't had the opportunity to look at those yet.
But
I think we've got
all of one or two places. I know when we put the outdoor dining into effect, we had to consider
Andover Pizza.
I don't know how Tom's place down the road fits into the dining establishment
regulations.
But he's been doing outdoor dining for a long time and
I don't know what permit, if any, we've got on that.
So
that's coming up in the near future.
Planning and zoning,
desired changes to our regulations,
and I know we've talked about we
currently don't have a frontage requirement for a standard lot. We've got width.
I'm under the impression that that was purely an administrative oversight when we lost that and pretty easy to put back. So
as we go through at some point a
update to our regulations,
we'll include that in there.
The other thing that we had was,
you know, it was somewhat a technicality,
but
the
property owners over on Hendy Road,
because of the wording in our regulations,
able to
go to the zoning board of appeals and get authorization permission to
build a home in a flood prone district.
I'm not sure that we thought that was the best idea in the world and
there's a couple of minor changes that we can make if we choose to that would
strengthen that prohibition.
And so I'll be looking at doing that.
I started working on changes to our sign regs a while ago that got unwieldy.
And so,
you know,
a bunch of stuff in there I don't think we're currently complying with.
I don't know that
we wanted to. I didn't necessarily want to make the regulations
mirror everything that we're currently doing.
But with a couple of elimination
of two or three words,
can make them at least constitutional
in all respect, get rid of that unconstitutionality
that
political signs are any different than any other signs. So I'll do that.
And those are the changes I added on this. I talked to Eric today about
when should we be doing our
08/24
referral to build, allow
the new community center
saying it's consistent with our plan of conservation and development.
So I put that on the list just to remember
to do.
And that
was all that's in there. Again, I encourage everybody to
read that bulletin I sent out from Hallor and Sage
on all this stuff. I've read through it a couple times now
and some of it's actually starting to make sense.
It certainly didn't on the first go through and I know that to a large part is going to be on me to
bring
some regulations
to you all so we can discuss it and make
things as appropriate.
>> One thing I, not to interrupt you Jeff, but one thing I did notice when I read that thing, they
want to change the accessory apartments to
two spots, one for each vehicle because they,
anybody else would think the same thing but there usually two people, know,
two spouses,
whatever in an apartment. They want two spots for that accessory apartment. Okay,
I hadn't picked up on that. Thanks Scott.
Think Yep. Our regulation should have said that.
>> Yep, we say one extra. Right, yep.
And again, when we
did the accessory apartment,
the thought process was
there's an
in law apartment for one person is at least what I had in mind, right, wrong or different, but we didn't limit it to that because we figured we couldn't
because
eventually that person would pass away and then what's the person supposed to do with the accessory apartment?
So we eliminated
that thought.
But
makes sense to have two parking spots for the accessory department.
But as other folks say, you know, as you catch me saying,
making commitments
to thin air that I'll go off and do something,
And you should say, so are you going to put it on that list that we're going to take a look at every now and then and make sure that we've done what we do?
At some point very soon, the Board of Selectmen will ask for our
annual report on what we've done
and what our goals are for next year, how we did on the goals for last year. This can form the basis for doing that as well. So that's why I put this in here. Any questions on Any other questions or comments on that?
>> Jed, this is Leanne. I inadvertently got disconnected and had to call back in. Could you just tell me really quickly
two or two and a half questions
about the affordable housing plan.
To make a long story short,
is it if we don't do certain things on the town level,
does whatever the state pass get imposed on us unless we show that we're doing something by ourselves?
>> That is certainly the case for accessory apartments.
Affordable housing plan,
we are required to have an affordable housing plan that reflects the desires of the citizens of hand how
we want to meet affordable housing with a goal of 10% in the town.
And we may not be the lowest percentage in the state for our town,
but it's in the lowest
two or three, if not the very bottom. So the
thought process is we may never meet the 10% goal, but at least we have a plan that tries to get there.
So
it'll be tied to funding. If we don't have a plan we might not get all our funding.
>> And I said I was going to make it quick but I'll make a two part question. Is any of this covered by our plan of conservation development?
Does that count toward it?
>> No.
Our plan needs to be consistent with the plan of conservation and development.
And if you look on the website,
there is
a piece
that can be included
in the
plan of conservation and development, but it wasn't ready when we issued it last time.
And
and I forget the title, but is affordable housing study or something like that. And
that is 90% of the solution. And so if we don't get our grant,
I will probably change the name of that from
affordable housing study to affordable housing plan and send it in. There's not a lot of requirements right this minute about what the plan has to have.
We just have to have a plan.
Now I'm sure that's going to change over the years where
the state figures out more than what we want to put into it. But as of right now, we just have to have a plan and we currently don't.
Don't have Did we have something ready but we didn't include it because it wasn't really ready? It was not ready at the time. I think that so our last plan of conservation and development was issued in 2015.
The date on this study is
'16.
And
there's also, if you look online,
there is a if you look under
appointed committees, there's a long term study
committee.
2019,
I think it is, they issued a long term study
plan.
And it talks about
affordable housing and all that stuff in there. So there's a lot out there. We need to take we know we don't have any affordable, we know we don't have much affordable housing, what are we doing to get there?
And we've done
several good things. We do have accessory apartment plan, which is a key.
We have the mixed use
floating rig
thing that allows affordable
housing. We made the
open space cluster subdivision so we could have smaller lots.
And we reduced the size of a house that
is
required to be built. So we as a town,
primarily through Eric's work,
did a lot of good stuff to get us that direction.
We just don't have a plan saying what we want to do
and how we're going to get there.
>> Okay,
thank you everyone. Thank you and thanks everyone for reiterating it. And did we
do F and G yet or did you skip those
while I was having to dial in again?
>> Pardon? No, we're going to move on to that right
I'm going to close it. It sounded
>> like maybe you were on new business when I called back in. So, okay. Thank you very much.
>> Is still affordable housing plan in recent legislation.
Okay. And there's a lot of it. Sorry to take so much time on that.
Return to life planning and zoning commission meetings. We were supposed to be meeting
live in person this month.
I was concerned
a little bit because I wasn't able to discuss it with Jim between last meeting and this meeting
that we go sit in the room and I could not use the computer that the town might provide to get things up on the new electronic screen in the community room
and
do even worse of a job than I do on presenting the stuff here. So
I
chickened out and we went back to holding
online meeting.
I guess the other thing that happened right after we decided to meet in person is
Mindy unfortunately put in her resignation
and said I live up in South Windsor,
not good to drive down there. And I certainly agree with that.
So
we're meeting
virtually tonight.
Since then, I've
thought
a little bit about
why I like these meetings.
And while I live very close to town hall and it's easy for me to get there,
I'm not sure that everybody does.
And
for instance, I know Kevin lives,
you can't live too far away and still be in Andover
but he's probably got the most inconvenient
drive to get here.
And if we wanted to ask our engineer
who lives in Lebanon
to attend the meeting.
It certainly makes it easier for him. Or Mark Branch. I don't know where Mark
lives.
But I know he doesn't live in Andover. And so
for a lot of different reasons,
I thought it was more convenient to people
to hop on the Zoom meeting.
My thoughts are that it's easier to present material in a Zoom meeting because
I'm used to using my computer and I can put it up. You know, we saw Chris Bell tonight put up some stuff for us to review
and
it's sitting right in front of me where I can see it good. I'm not sure I can see it as well on that
large screen that we've got in the community room.
And I know the acoustics in that room aren't very good. And I can
crank up my volume and not bother any of you and hear
all that I want.
So with that,
I said there are some nice advantages to continuing on Zoom.
But I'll bring it back to the Commission. I know
Abby lives
not too far away.
I kind of like doing it in Zoom for the time being. I really don't know where this Delta variant of the coronavirus thing is headed.
And this is pretty easy.
If there's some big opposition,
you know, opposition
is I don't get a chance to
shoot the breeze with each of you folks and get to know you each, it is people.
I've never been able to say hi to Mindy and here she is leaving already.
I regret that.
That's not a great thing. So that's the piece
that
we're downside on.
And maybe we have, you know, when the weather's nice, an in person meeting,
occasionally
just to work on regs or something like that when we don't have other stuff going on. But
I wanted to bring that back to the Commission for discussion.
But if there was no big opposition,
I would suggest that we continue using Zoom for at least
a little bit until I'm convinced. Let other people work the bugs out of displaying everything.
I know the town's working on how to do a hybrid meeting,
which I think is a good idea. I just don't know how to do it and I didn't want to
jump off on that until we didn't have the bugs worked out. So if
somebody really got a hard spot and wants to get together,
I'll say we can do that but otherwise I kind of like doing it this way.
Any thoughts?
>> I've
said before that I prefer in person and I still do.
>> And that was a big part of why I wanted to try it because
of your input and the fact other people were doing that.
I don't know what I don't know how many other commissions are actually meeting in person or not yet.
But
anyhow,
when I attended a Board of Education meeting,
I liked the way they did it.
I don't know that we over at Town Hall are geared up to do that yet.
That
was my decision on that. Leanne, what's your view? You're the one I can't ever see. I don't see your expression when you're frowning at me.
>> Well,
I don't think I frown at you too often, if ever. But
basically,
I now have to drive around Bunker Hill Road to Coventry to go anywhere.
So I don't mind doing that. But
I
could go either way. I'm fortunate that I don't have an underlying condition that makes me reluctant to go out to these kind of things and I'm fully vaccinated. On the other hand, the Delta variant is a concern and according to CNN,
cases are going up all over the country, although they're mostly among unvaccinated people.
So
I'm fine with continuing to meet
over Zoom. Okay.
>> And I think for at least, you know, for next month, I'm going to plan on meeting on Zoom.
I
recognize that there are some drawbacks to it, but there are some advantages to too.
Filling of vacancies.
The good news is
that the vacancies are filled.
We've got a full commission at this point.
Steve is
I'm sure that when we ask you to vote on all these things and you hadn't had the benefit of sitting in on any of the discussions, let alone the chance to familiarize yourself with the regs,
that's what get
paid the big bucks for.
So
there's
a lot to learn,
we'll get there.
But I certainly appreciate having Steve on the Commission and
look forward to working with him as I enjoy working
with all you folks on this and
come to the best answers that we can. So welcome, Steve.
Anything you want? Thanks, Jed. Tell us about yourself
in two minutes or less kind of
deal.
>> Sure. I know everybody's pretty tired.
Long meeting. But happy
to be
part of the team here.
My wife Charlotte and I moved to Andover
two years ago. We bought for anybody that remembers Priscilla Bronkey, we bought Priscilla's
house on the lake.
Totally. Yeah.
>> Never met Priscilla, but I heard great
stories about her.
Anyway, we want to do our part to contribute.
And I was a little surprised
to get elected after only living here two years, but happy to serve. And
I am an engineer, undergraduate
degree in engineering.
I haven't
done any hardcore engineering in several years. I'm more
management, helping to run an engineering services business
here in Connecticut.
But
this kind of stuff really interests me.
And I obviously am going to be drinking from a fire hose for a little while. So if you guys can be patient with me, I appreciate that. But
I'm sure I'll come up to speed pretty fast.
>> So Steve is also on
Alpoa
and Alma.
So for a guy who's been in town all of two years, there's been a lot of
volunteer time sucking them up and
here you go. So
great to have
Steve join us.
The other addition
is Abby Winter who I
forget
how long
who is well let me just say I know Abby is another
recent addition to the town of Andover, hasn't been here too long
and again you know is involved in just
a ton of stuff to make Andover Dick. So how about tell us a little bit about
you there, Abi?
>> Yeah, absolutely. So I moved here last October
and
since moving here I've
dove in into working over and over and
starting a community garden in town. If you've heard of it, please stop by. It's right behind town hall,
as well as helping onboard here. I'd love I'm really excited to learn more about planning and zoning and land use. I currently am working in the water
monitoring group. I'm really interested in land use and seeing how you all
contribute to this really interesting piece of land we have here in Andover.
Abby, you're a graduate student over at UConn?
>> Yes,
Someone studying environmental science. Are there?
Environmental science and energy. Yep, so
>> especially for the inland wetlands folks,
works out.
That's right up Abby's alley but she is certainly very passionate about all this stuff that we're doing and
very nice to have her here.
Thank you. Susan
>> England couldn't join us. She has other obligations tonight, but she went from being the full time Commission member to
an alternate. So we've got the three alternates,
Kevin, Anne and Susan now.
Life is good. We're a full house. So that
is just great.
Oh, I guess we've got minutes to approve from the last time.
And so
with
that,
I can only say thank you, Mindy, for the fantastic job you've
done throughout your tenure here
on writing the minutes.
I will ask
well, I guess first, I'm looking for a motion to approve the minutes from the June 21 meeting.
I move to approve the minutes.
>> Thank you.
You, Ian.
Looking for a second. Sooner we second, sooner we get to go.
Second.
Thank you, Scott.
Any comments on the minutes? Any discussion?
Again,
I thought they were
very well done, Mindy. I'll embarrass myself by two or three typos
on page three
paragraph
5B
under
the second line in there,
applicants in and, which should be an A N.
At the bottom of that page,
third paragraph up from the bottom, second line,
coverage
needs the E at the end of the word there.
And then the last little paragraph there,
if the extension is granted instead of ingranted,
So and then on the
very last page
at the top there on the special meeting site walk of June 1,
it's got we
move to approve the meeting minutes
as presented,
and it says Scott Person moved. It should be Scott Person seconded.
And so
any other comments on the minutes?
Hearing none, call for a vote. Anne?
Aye.
Scott?
Leigh Ann?
>> Oh, I just saw something.
Sorry. Oh,
under
sorry. Now I'm trying to backtrack.
Something minor.
Under five d,
discussion action
about the dog kennel.
Yep.
>> The
second paragraph,
SBB stated that operates as a
as a doggy
daycare
probably just meant to say as a doggy daycare
five d
>> I sorry it's no big deal I'm trying to do this quickly yep no I've got you so on
>> page five
item 5D,
second paragraph,
Scott Beebe stated that he
operates
as a
doggy daycare.
So we need to add the word he
and eliminate the word does.
I think so. Yep. Good comment, Leanne. So we will add that to
our list of procedures.
>> I will go back and vote one more time starting from the top.
Aye.
Scott? Aye.
Leigh Ann?
Aye. Steve?
>> Since I didn't attend the meeting, can I just abstain?
>> You can, yep.
Thank you. And I vote aye as well. So the motion
passes four-zero-one
with Steve Nelson abstaining.
Okay.
Agent Halsey, any correspondence
or administrative reports?
>> Not much to report. I I have been
working limited hours the last month. I do have a couple of enforcement
actions that I
have put on put on hold. Hopefully, we'll be moving forward on at
this time. A lot of activity given, for whatever reason,
backlog of permits,
working through them.
Other than that, I have nothing new to report.
>> Okay.
Any questions for our zoning agent?
Hearing none, move on to commission discussion, miscellaneous.
>> Ed, could you just quickly go over
return to live planning and zoning commission? I got kicked out again tonight,
Greg, when you were talking about that. Yep. So
>> at least for the next meeting,
we're going to do another Zoom.
My rationale for that is
it is
so convenient to have people
pop in who maybe don't live right next door to town hall, whether it be the lawyer
or engineer
or even
applicants and their engineers and that sort of thing.
So there's the ease of that. I like the ease of presenting materials electronically
on the screen that's right in front of everybody.
And I also think the acoustics are better.
We're able to understand more clearly than we can in the community room.
The only downside is that we
don't get a chance to really
meet each other as people, which I think is very important.
With technology today,
that's what's driving us away from getting to know who our neighbors are. And I think there is a big detriment to that but
for the time being with I
think the advantages outweigh the disadvantages
and until I get
comfortable with the technology over there in the community center and how that's going to work,
would like to continue to do a virtual meeting.
Okay, thank you. Yep.
>> Any other
discussion miscellaneous
thoughts?
Okay, moving on to the public comment.
I'm sure that we don't
have any public remaining here.
Very good. And so before I get a motion to
approve, Abby, you now see what your challenge is ahead.
Take all this discussion
and try to distill it somehow.
How Ian has done that so well, I don't know.
But get the secret from her,
not Ann Mindy.
Ann just happens to be sitting in the little box right next to you as I look it up there.
Mindy has done an exceptional job and I know you'll do
just as well, but there's got to be a trick in there, I don't know what the trick is. So get it for Mindy before she's gone.
And welcome to
Abby and Steve.
At this point,
looking for a motion to adjourn.
>> I move that we adjourn the meeting. Thank you, Anne. Any second?
Leanne,
>> I'll second. Thank you, Lee Ann.
All in favor say aye.
Aye. Any
opposed?
The motion carries unanimously,
five-zero-zero.
Thank you everybody and good night and I appreciate all the work that all of you do to support the Commission.
I enjoy working with all of you. So thank you.
Thank you.